Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- Administrative Records, 1953-1983; I.
  - Governor Thornburgh Address on Human Services, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Growth, Opportunity; Security: Commitment to Pennsylvania Human Services" Pamphlet, May 10, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35, Item 1)
      A pamphlet with a statement by Richard L. Thornburgh on the need to ensure the development of, and provide opportunities for all Pennsylvania Citizens during his campaign for Governor of Pennsylvania.
  - DPW: Helen O'Bannon Speech to ACC-PARC Regarding Advocacy, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Tom Forester Speech Annual Meeting of United Cerebral Palsy Association, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Installation of Officers Program, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Events and Presentations Flyers, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "All You Ever Wanted to Know About Residential Services for the Mentally Retarded but Were Afraid to Ask" Flyer, December 12, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39, Item 1)
      A flyer for an ACC-PARC hosted event that offered citizens a discussion and presentations on the state of residential care for residents of PA state schools.
  - The Family Trust Logo, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - ACC-PARC Newsletters, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - ACC-PARC Newsletters, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - ACC-PARC Newsletters, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - ACC-PARC Newsletters, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - PARC Newsletter, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - News Clippings, c. 1950-1960 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - News Clippings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Children Limited Newspapers, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous News Clippings Summer 1967-January 1984, 1967-1984 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - News Clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - PA Mental Retardation Program Summary of Achievements, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - News Clippings Regarding Opportunity Centers/PARC-Way, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Newsletters: Allegheny Accents, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - ACC-PARC Allegheny Accents Newsletter, c. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 76, Item 1)
      An issue of the ACC-PARC's Allegheny Accents newsletter. The newsletter summarizes the events and activities completed by the organization in the year 1975.
    - ACC-PARC Allegheny Accents Newsletter (2), April 1976 (Box 1, Folder 76, Item 2)
      A copy of the April 1976 ACC-PARC's Allegheny Accents newsletter. The newsletter summarizes the events, activities, and ongoing issues regarding individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
    - ACC-PARC Allegheny Accents Newsletter (3), July 1976 (Box 1, Folder 76, Item 3)
      A copy of the July 1976 ACC-PARC's Allegheny Accents newsletter. The newsletter summarizes the events, activities, and ongoing issues regarding individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
  - Topical Files, 1974-1982; 1.
    This subseries contains administrative records pertaining to certain initiatives undertaken by ACC-PARC. Primarily comprised of correspondence and reports, these files document campaigns and projects on topics such as alternatives to institutions, community living arrangements, and zoning for group homes.
    - Alternatives to Institutions Campaign Records I, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Alternatives to Institutions Campaign Records II, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - Letter About Public Meeting with Frank S. Beal, June 7, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 52, Item 1)
        A letter that informs the recipients of a meeting with Secretary of Welfare, Frank S. Beal, in downtown Pittsburgh. The letter invites parents and families to share their concerns for their children and demand alternatives to institutions.
      - "Pretty Words? Or a Real Commitment?" ACC-PARC Handout, June 1976 (Box 1, Folder 52, Item 2)
        An informational handout by ACC-PARC regarding the alternatives to state institutions for individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities. The handout includes quotes by officials from the Department of Public Welfare and facts about the lack of programming and non-institutional residential facilities.
    - Alternatives to Institutions Campaign Records, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Community Living Arrangements Program Records, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - Parents and Guardians of Residents at Western State School and Hospital Position Statement, August 11, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 54, Item 1)
        A position statement by Harry Goldberg, president of the Western State School and Hospital Parents Group, accusing both the state and PARC of misunderstanding and mishandling problems at Western State School and Hospital.
      - Budget Data for Community Living Arrangements Program, 1974-1977, c. 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 54, Item 2)
        A copy of the data gathered for the Community Living Arrangements Program. The data includes available funds, the number of operation programs, the number of residents in CLAs, and previous living arrangements.
    - Community Living Arrangements Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Community Living Arrangements Residential Services Position Paper, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Community Living Arrangements Residents List, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Group Homes City Planning Commission Minutes, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      - City Planning Commission Meeting Minutes, October 11, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 58, Item 1)
        Minutes for the City Planning Commission's October 11, 1977 meeting. The Commission discussed the possibility of a group home run by the Children's Aid Home for Special People non-profit. The minutes contain handwritten notes, possibly written by Bob Nelkin, throughout the pages.
    - News Clippings Regarding Group Homes, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Senate Bill #94 - Zoning for Group Homes Files I, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Senate Bill #94 - Zoning for Group Homes Files II, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      - Community Living Facilities Task Force Minutes, January 12, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 61, Item 1)
        Minutes from the January 1978 meeting of the Community Living Facilities Task Force, amendments to Senate Bill 94 was discussed. Senate Bill 94 dealt with changing zoning laws to allow group homes in all residential areas in Pennsylvania.
    - Senate Bill #94 - Zoning for Group Homes Files I, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      - Letter from Robert Hoffman to Thomas Halloran on legal concerns related to Senate Bill 94, February 3, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 62, Item 1)
        A letter from Robert Hoffman addressing Thomas Halloran's concern that Senate Bill 94 would allow dangerously mentally ill individuals to live in group homes in all residential areas.
      - Information Compiled on Senate Bill 94, c. 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 62, Item 2)
        A copy of the information gathered, probably by PARC, used to support Senate Bill 94. Senate Bill 94 allowed the zoning of group homes in all residential areas. This packet includes a cost analysis, statistics from polls, and addresses the concern of property values.
    - Senate Bill #94 - Zoning for Group Homes Files II, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      - Legislative Action, March 31, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 1)
        A copy of PARC's March 31, 1978 issue of the Legislative Action newsletter. This issue focuses on legislative issues that include discussion on the passage of Senate Bill 94, which allowed zoning for group homes in all residential areas.
      - House Roll Call on Senate Bill 94, March 14, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 2)
        A copy of the roll call from the Pennsylvania House of Representatives listing how members voted on Senate Bill 94, which the zoning of group homes in all residential areas. Subscribers to PARC's Legislative Action magazine received this roll call with the March 31, 1978 issue.
      - Community Living Facilities Task Force Minutes (2), July 14, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 3)
        Minutes from the July 1978 meeting of the Community Living Facilities Task Force. The Task Force discussed the City of Pittsburgh's stance on Senate Bill 94, legislation that allowed the zoning of group homes in all residential areas.
      - Summary in Support of Senate Bill 94, c. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 4)
        A list of people who will be affected by Senate Bill 94 (legislation that allows the zoning of group homes in all residential areas), including individuals with physical disabilities and individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities of all ages.
      - Proposed Amendment to Section 1 of Senate Bill 94, c. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 5)
        A proposed amendment to Senate Bill 94's first section specifying the type of individuals with mental illness able to live in group homes zoned for residential areas.
      - Proposed Amendment to Section 4 of Senate Bill 94, c. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 6)
        A proposed amendment to Section 4 of Senate Bill 94 dealing with provisions for individuals if the nearest group home to them is at capacity.
      - Senate Bill 94, Group Homes, Zoning, March 14, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 63, Item 7)
        An updated version of Senate Bill 94 with amendments from the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. Senate Bill 94 allowed the zoning of group homes in all residential areas.
    - Pennsylvania Legislature: Zoning, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  This series primarily consists of meeting minutes, notes, correspondence, reports and case file records that document the activities of ACC-PARC's SSH and Interim Care Committee. The records contained in this series document the efforts of this committee to discover and expose social welfare concerns at residential care facilities for people with disabilities. In particular, the case file records in this series document reports and investigations into human rights violations discovered at residential care facilities.
  - State Schools and Hospital Interim Care Committee Records I, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Draft Agreements Between ACC-PARC and Department of Public Welfare Letter from Charles Peters, November 13, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 1)
      A copy of a letter sent to Charles Peters, executive director of ACC-PARC, that contained a draft of agreements between ACC-PARC and the Department of Public Works discussing how the organizations will work together.
    - Information Gathered for Virginia Thornburgh Interview on Closeup Program, October 24, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 2)
      Background information on ACC-PARC and Virginia Thornburgh for Don Cannon and Bob Sprague, the hosts of the television show Closeup for an upcoming interview.
    - Questions for Ginny Thornburgh Interview, c. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 3)
      A copy of questions asked and Virginia Thornburgh's answers during a media interview regarding State Centers and integration. Thornburgh was First Vice president of ACC-PARC and chairwoman of ACC-PARC's State School and Hospital and Interim Care Committee at this time.
    - Parents Training Seminar Flyer, February 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 4)
      A flyer advertising ACC-PARC's Parent Training Seminar aimed to inform parents what life entails inside state institutions for their children.
    - Right to Education in State Institutions Memo from Bob Nelkin, December 13, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 5)
      A memo from Bob Nelkin to the State Schools and Hospitals and Interim Care Committee on recent resolutions at a Harrisburg meeting of the Right to Education Masters.
    - Children's Rehabilitation Center Unannounced Visit Notes, November 29, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 6)
      Transcribed notes taken during an announced visit by ACC-PARC to the Children's Rehabilitation Center in Butler, PA. Nelkin was a member of this inspection team that observed the condition of the center.
    - ACC-PARC Residential Services Committee Listing of Objectives Draft, November 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 7)
      A list of objectives for the ACC-PARC Residential Services Committee, focusing on reforms to ensure resident's rights for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities residing in state institutions.
    - Report Concerning A Call About Children's Rehabilitation Center, Butler, PA, December 29, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 8)
      A note by Bob Nelkin regarding a phone call from an employee of the Children's Rehabilitation Center. The employee discussed issues at the center following a strike. This document includes hand-written notes, possibly by Nelkin, inquiring how ACC-PARC reacted to this call.
    - January 1973 Visit to Children's Rehabilitation Center Notes, January 1, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 9)
      Transcribed notes during a visit by ACC-PARC to Children's Rehabilitation Center in Butler, PA. Bob Nelkin was a member of the visitation team that noted inadequate staffing and programming at the center.
    - December 1972 Visit to Children's Rehabilitation Center, December 29, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 10)
      Transcribed notes during a visit by ACC-PARC to Children's Rehabilitation Center in Butler, PA during a strike of childcare workers. Bob Nelkin was a member of the visitation team.
    - Letter from Ralph Meador to Charles Peters, December 21, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 11)
      A letter sent to Charles Peters about the Nancy W. situation at Polk State School and Hospital. Meador agrees that it is inappropriate to restrict communications between residents and their families, and says that this right will be included on the "Bill of Rights" for individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities. Meador also states that he will instruct Dr. McClelland to review and revise his policy on using the telephone.
    - Letter from Mr. W. to Dr. James R. McClelland, September 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 12)
    - Reforming the State Schools and Interim Care Committee Statement, November 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 13)
    - State School and Hospital and State-Subsidized Interim Care Facilities Memo, December 1, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 14)
      A memo from Charles Peters regarding recent visits to State School and Hospitals and Interim Care Facilities, alternatives to institutions, and the problem of individuals without disabilities placed in state schools and hospitals.
    - ACC-PARC News Release, November 30, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 15)
      An ACC-PARC news release describing an upcoming educational program hosted by the organization regarding residential services for individuals with disabilities. The program aimed to inform citizens of the life of residents in state schools and institutions.
    - ACC-PARC President Dr. Norman Mulgrave Memo, October 25, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 16)
      A memo sent by ACC-PARC President Dr. Norman Mulgrave regarding the possibility of a Civil Rights suit between ACC-PARC and the state.
    - Letter to Kenneth Winograd on Residential Care Facilities, August 24, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 17)
      A letter sent to Kenneth Winograd from Louis Reid on behalf of a group of architects, engineers, and concerned citizens. Reid and these groups asked Winograd to use his influence to permit the use of conventional residences, duplexes, and triplexes as suitable living arrangements for group homes for individuals with developmental and intellectual disabilities.
    - Department of Public Welfare News Release Memo, September 17, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 18)
      A memo sent to regional PARC organizations by Patricia Clapp, president of PARC, with copies of a news release from the Department of Public Works regarding state services for persons with disabilities.
    - Letter from Charles Peters on Investigating Private Institutions, July 25, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 19)
      A letter sent to Robert Casey from Charles Peters regarding the possibilities and logistics of investigating private institutions that provide services for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities like the Allegheny Valley School and the Laurel House in Pittsburgh and Fayette County respectively.
    - Charles Peters Residential Care Memo, July 11, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 20)
      A memo from Charles Peters to the ACC-PARC Board of Directors urging them to bring greater awareness to the plight of Pennsylvanians with intellectual and developmental disabilities.
    - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Joseph Diannabell Regarding White Deer Interim Care Facility Visit, July 24, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 21)
      A letter from Virginia Thornburgh, chairwoman of the State School and Hospital and Interim Care Committee, to Joseph Diannabell, director of the White Deer Interim Care Facility, expressing a desire to visit the facility in early August.
  - State Schools and Hospital and Interim Care Committee Records II, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Memo on Use of Somerset State Hospital, March 13, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 66, Item 1)
      A memo from Bob Nelkin to other ACC-PARC officers regarding the decision to not place individuals with mental illnesses at Somerset State Hospital.
    - ACC-PARC Residential Care Committee Visit to Idlewood Group Home Notes, November 4, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 2)
      Transcribed notes made by a member of the ACC-PARC Residential Care Committee during a 1973 Visit to Idlewood Group Home.
    - Nation's MR Institutions Studied Data, c. 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 3)
      A copy of a study that ranked the residential care in state institutions across the nation for the fiscal year of 1971.
    - ACC-PARC Residential Care Committee Meeting Minutes, October 14, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 4)
      Meeting minutes for the ACC-PARC's Residential Care Committee. In this meeting the committee discussed the proposed 9200 regulations for residential service facilities.
    - Letter from Charles Peters to Ford Thompson Regarding Polk and Western State School and Hospitals, June 18, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 5)
      A letter from Charles Peters, executive director of ACC-PARC, to Ford Thompson of the Department of Public Welfare regarding the conditions at Polk and Western State School and Hospitals. Peters is also offering his goals for the institutions to ensure humane treatment of residents.
    - Letter from J. Shane Creamer to Charles Peters, May 2, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 6)
      A letter from J. Shane Creamer, Attorney General of Pennsylvania, to Executive Director of ACC-PARC Charles Peters. Creamer informs Peters that he forwarded Peters' letter regarding the state's lien law to the Office of the Deputy Attorney General.
    - Letter from Charles Peters to J. Shane Creamer, Attorney General of Pennsylvania, April 28, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 7)
      A letter from Charles Peters, executive director of ACC-PARC, to Attorney General of Pennsylvania J. Shane Creamer. Peters asks Creamer about the state's lien law and the ability to claim funds from the family of residents within state schools and hospitals.
    - Letter from Charles Peters to Thomas Lamb, May 17, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 8)
      A letter from Charles Peters, executive director of ACC-PARC to Pennsylvania State Senator Thomas Lamb. Peters expresses enthusiasm for Lamb's letter about introducing legislation to reform lien laws. Peters suggests removing family financial obligations after the age of 21.
    - Letter from Thomas Lamb to Charles Peters, May 11, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 9)
      A letter from Pennsylvania State Senator Thomas Lamb to Executive Director of ACC-PARC Charles Peters. Lamb informs Peters that the Department of Welfare and the Department of Justice has no interest in dropping the claims against families of state school residents. However, Lamb states that the governor pledges to eliminate this practice over the next five years.
    - Letter from ACC-PARC to KDKA Draft, c. 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 10)
      A draft of a letter meant to be sent to KDKA, applauding the station for its dedication to the rights of the intellectually disabled. However, the author of this letter informs the station that other complicated issues cause problems for the state schools and hospitals across the state. For example, the author discusses the funding and lack of community program staff.
    - Parent Training Workshop Ideas, February 24, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 11)
      An image of a list of ideas to raise awareness and ways to improve residential services in state schools and hospitals following a discussion at a parent training workshop.
    - Dr. Burrow Appointment News Release, March 19, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 12)
      A copy of the Department of Public Welfare's news release regarding the appointment of Dr. Burrow as the acting superintendent of Ebensburg State School and Hospital.
    - Schedule of Patient Distribution and Costs by Facility as of June 30, 1971 Memo, March 9, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 13)
      A memo sent by Bob Nelkin to members of the State School and Interim Care Committee regarding the number of Allegheny County citizens in different State Institutions, and the costs for care of these citizens.
    - Draft of Letter to Helene Wohlgemuth Regarding Unannounced Visits, November 19, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 14)
      A draft of a letter for Secretary Wohlgemuth of the Department of Public Welfare regarding unannounced visits to state-run and private institutions. The letter includes recommendations for reviews, training, and licensing.
    - ACC-PARC News Release (2), November 14, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 65, Item 15)
      An ACC-PARC press release praising the Department of Public Welfare for investigating interim care facilities, but condemning the decision to place residents in mental health hospitals.
  - SSH Investigation Team Minutes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - SSH Investigation Team Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Letter from Charles Peters to Edward Goldman, October 30, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 68, Item 1)
      A letter from ACC-PARC Executive Director Charles Peters to Edward Goldman of the Department of Public Welfare. Peters informs Goldman on the upcoming plans of the investigation team, and the need to prevent any future incidents.
    - Letter from Helene Wohlgemuth to Virginia Thornburgh, February 15, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 68, Item 2)
      A letter from Secretary Wohlgemuth to Virginia Thornburgh of ACC-PARC regarding the Department of Public Welfare's task force on interim care.
    - Meeting with William and Wallace Flood Memo, February 14, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 68, Item 3)
      A memo summarizing a meeting between Stanley Meyers of ACC-PARC, William Flood, president of Enterprises for Social Progress, and his brother Wallace Flood. The trio discussed the operation and issues of Park Nursing Home.
    - Telegram to Governor Milton Shapp and Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth, October 20, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 68, Item 4)
      A telegram sent to Governor Milton Shapp and Secretary Helen Wohlgemuth of the Department of Public Welfare by a visitation team of ACC-PARC members. The telegram informs the two of dehumanizing conditions at Mountain Top Interim Care Facility.
  - TPU Staffing Patient Reports, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Easter Seal Society Case File Records, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Jamel D. Case File Records, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Jimmy A. Case File Records, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Case Files and Notes, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Bob Nelkin Memo, February 21, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 73, Item 1)
      A memo from Bob Nelkin to other ACC-PARC members regarding a former Western State School and Hospital resident, Gary, and his experience after transferring out of WSSH.
  - PA Association for Retarded Children s. PA Civil Action Suit, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 77)